<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3168 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3168.xml">
]>
<rfc submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-huang-alto-mowie-for-network-aware-app-03" category="std" ipr="trust200902">

	<?rfc strict="yes"?>
	<?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc text-list-symbols="*o+-"?>
	<?rfc toc="yes"?>
	<front>
	<title>MoWIE for Network Aware Application</title>
	<author initials="Y." surname="Jia" fullname="Yuhang Jia">
	<organization>Tencent</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Flat 9, No. 10 West Building, Xi Bei Wang East Road</street>
	<street>Beijing</street>
	<street>100090</street>
	<street>China</street>
	</postal>
	<email>tonyjia@tencent.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author initials="Y." surname="Zhang" fullname="Yunfei Zhang">
	<organization>Tencent</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Flat 9, No. 10 West Building,Xi Bei Wang East Road</street>
	<street>Beijing</street>
	<street>100090</street>
	<street>China</street>
	</postal>
	<email>yanniszhang@tencent.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author initials="Y. R." surname="Yang" fullname="Y. Richard Yang">
	<organization>Yale University</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Watson 208A, 51 Prospect Street</street>
	<street>New Haven,  CT 06511</street>
	<street>United States of America</street>
	</postal>
	<email>yang.r.yang@yale.edu</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author initials="G." surname="Li" fullname="Gang Li">
	<organization abbrev="CMRI">China Mobile Research Institute</organization>
	<address><postal><street>No.32, Xuanwumenxi Ave, Xicheng District</street>
	<street>Beijing</street>
	<street>100053</street>
	<street>China</street>
	</postal>
	<email>ligangyf@chinamobile.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author initials="Y." surname="Lei" fullname="Yixue Lei">
	<organization>Tencent</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Flat 9, No. 10 West Building,Xi Bei Wang East Road</street>
	<street>Beijing</street>
	<street>100090</street>
	<street>China</street>
	</postal>
	<email>yixuelei@tencent.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<author initials="Y." surname="Han" fullname="Yunbo Han">
	<organization>Tencent</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Tencent Building, No. 10000 Shennan Avenue, Nanshan District</street>
	<street>Shenzhen</street>
	<street>518000</street>
	<street>China</street>
	</postal>
	<email>yunbohan@tencent.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

   <author initials="Sabine" surname="Randriamasy" fullname="S. Randriamasy">
	<organization>Nokia</organization>
	<address><postal><street>Nokia Bell Labs</street>
	<street>Nozay</street>
	<street>United States of America</street>
	</postal>
	<email>sabine.randriamasy@nokia-bell-labs.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<date year="2021" month="July" day="11"/>
	<workgroup>ALTO</workgroup>
	<abstract><t>
   With the quick deployment of 5G networks in the world, cloud-based
   interactive services such as cloud gaming have gained substantial
   attention and are regarded as potential killer applications.  To
   ensure users' quality of experience (QoE), a cloud interactive
   service may require not only high bandwidth (e.g., high-resolution
   media transmission) but also low delay (e.g., low latency and low
   lagging).  However, the bandwidth and delay experienced by a mobile
   and wireless user can be dynamic, as a function of many factors, and
   unhandled changes can substantially compromise the user's QoE.  In this
   document, we investigate network-aware applications (NAA), which
   realize cloud based interactive services with improved QoE, by
   efficient utilization of a solution named Mobile and Wireless Information Exposure
   (MoWIE). In particular, this document demonstrates, through
   realistic evaluations, that mobile network information such as MCS
   (Modulation and Coding Scheme) can effectively expose the dynamicity
   of the underlying network and can be made available to applications
   through MoWIE; using such information, the applications can then
   adapt key control knobs such as media codec scheme, encapsulation, and
   application layer processing to minimize QoE deduction. Based on the
   evaluations, we discuss how the MoWIE features can define extensions of the ALTO protocol, 
   to expose more lower-layer and finer grain network dynamics.</t>

	</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
	<section title="Introduction of Network-aware Applications" anchor="sect-1"><t>
   With the quick and wide deployment of 5G networks in the world, more
   applications are become available as remote cloud-based
   applications. These include new and amazing applications such as cloud AR/VR/MR.  
   Many traditional interactive, daily business applications are also becoming widely used 
   as cloud applications, with the help of mobile networks and cloud, e.g., cloud video
   conference. Especially, during the coronavirus pandemic in 2020,
   many people had to stay at home and work/study remotely, and the usage
   of cloud applications, including cloud-based online courses, cloud-based conferencing, 
   and cloud gaming, have surged significantly.</t>

	<t>
   To optimize QoE for end users using mobile networks,
   many cloud applications utilize information about the mobile network status, e.g.,
   delay, bandwidth, and jitter, to dynamically balance the generated media
   traffic and the rendering/mixing in the cloud. Currently, such an
   application assumes the network as a black box and continuously uses
   client or server measurements to detect network characteristics,
   and then adaptively changes its network-related parameters as well as logical function
   of the application.  However, when only application information is
   utilized, the QoE that an application can achive can be limited in some cases.
   First, information from application side may have relatively long delay. When a user
   enters location with bad network connectivity such as an elevator or an underground
   garage, the application will not receive such information
   immediately.  As a result, the buffer of video application may have a
   high chance to run out.  Then the screen will freeze and users' QoE
   will be harmed.  Besides, the application does not have information
   about other users in the cell.  Thus, it cannot know how many
   resources it can get and when it will change.  If other users enter
   the cell and compete on the usage of the resource, the application layer may misjudge
   the resource and request a high bitrate.  Then the delay will
   increase and QoE will drop.  Some information from network layer like
   physical resource block (PRB) information and utilization rate can
   help to describe how many resources the user will get and how many
   users are competing with it.  Such information is helpful to predict
   the network and streaming videos. However, the application cannot get
   those kinds of information yet.</t>

	<t>
   Mobile network is always pursuing standard solutions to get network
   dynamic indicators that can be used by applications.  In 3GPP, many IP-based QoE mechanism are reused. For example, 
   ECN <xref target="RFC3168"/> has been
   supported by the 4G radio station (eNB) to provide CE(Congestion
   Encountered) information to the IMS application to perform 
   Adaptive Bitrate (ABR) <xref target="TS26.114"/>.The application can downgrade the
   bit rate after receiving the CE indication, but does not know the exact
   bit rate to be selected. DSCP <xref target="RFC2474"/> is used to difference the
   QoS class and paging strategy<xref target="TS23.501"/>, but typically the application
   cannot dynamically change the DSCP to improve bit rate based on the
   network status.  DASH <xref target="MPEGDASH"/> is a MPEG standard widely used for
   the applications to detect the throughput of the network based on the
   current throughput and buffering states and adaptively select the
   next segment of video streaming with a suitable bitrate in order to
   avoid re-buffering. SAND-DASH <xref target="TS26.247"/> defines the mechanism
   that the network/server can provide available throughput to the 
   applications; in such case, the better bitrate can be selected by DASH
   application.</t>

	<t>
   In 5G cellular networks, network capability exposure has been
   specified to allow the 5G system to expose user device
   location and network status towards the 3rd party application servers
   modeled as AF (Application Function) <xref target="TS23.501"/>. In such a case, the AF
   can request the 5G to establish a dedicated QoS Flow to transport an
   IP flow with the AF-provided QoS requirements. Via certain measurement, 
   network internal status including congestion can be exposed and optimization 
   can be carried out for cellular network <xref target="PBECC"/>.</t> 
   
   <t>
   5G also can
   provide QNC (QoS Notification Control) to the AF if the
   GBR(Guaranteed Bitrate) of the established GBR QoS Flow cannot be
   fulfilled, and the AF can change the bitrate after receiving the QNC
   notification.  But the AF still does not know which bitrate to be
   selected. So 5G enhances the QNC with providing a list of
   AQPs (alternative QoS profiles). With AQP, a 5G network provides
   a subset of supported AQPs with the QNC, and then the AF selects a bit
   rate from 5G network supported AQPs. In such a case, the GBR can
   fulfill again if the radio state of user is changed.  QoS
   prediction is realized by network function inside 5GC to collect and
   analyze the status and parameters from the 5G network entities, and
   deliver the analytics results towards the entity such as application
   server. </t> 
   
   <t>
   However, both network capability exposure and QoS
   prediction solutions are designed for 5G access and core network,
   which cannot cover the whole end-to-end network.  How to enable the
   application to be aware of the lower layer networks in Internet
   scenario is an important area for both industrial and academic
   researchers, that is addressed by MoWIE. </t>
   
   <t>
   MoWIE is a solution that aims 
   to realize real-time provisioning of cellular radio network information 
   by networks to applications, thus helping service providers to achieve a better policy control and 
   to improve user experience. The benefits of the MoWIE concept/solution have been 
   experimented on several use cases, detailed in 4.1.
</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Use Cases of Network-Aware Application (NAA)" anchor="sect-2"><t>
   There are three typical NAAs, cloud gaming, low delay live show, and
   cloud VR, whose QoE can be largely enhanced with the help of MoWIE.</t>

	<section title="Cloud Gaming" anchor="sect-2.1"><t>
   As mentioned above, cloud gaming is widely used and this kind of games requires low latency and highly
   reliable transmission of motion tracking data from user to gaming
   server in the cloud, as well as low latency and high data rate
   transmission of processed visual content from gaming server cloud to
   the user devices.  Cloud gaming is regarded as one major killer
   application as well as traffic contributor to wireless and cellular
   networks including 5G.  The major advantages of cloud gaming are easy
   &amp; quick starting (no/less need to download and install a high volume 
   software in the user device), less cost and process load in user
   device and it is also regarded as anti-cheating measure. Thus, cloud
   gaming has become a competitive replacement for console gaming
   using cheaper PC or laptop.  In order to support high quality cloud
   gaming services, the application need to get the information from the
   network layer, e.g., the data rate value or range which lower layer
   can provide in order to perform rendering and encoding, during which
   the application in the cloud can adopt different parameters to adjust
   the size of produced visual content within a time period.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Low Delay Live Show" anchor="sect-2.2"><t>
   In 2019, over 500 million active users were using online personal
   live show services in China and there are 4 million simultaneous
   online audience watching a celebrity's show.  Low delay live show
   requires the close interaction between application and network.</t>

	<t>
   Compared with conventional broadcast services, this service is
   interactive, which means that audience can be involved and they are
   able to provide feedback to the anchor.  For example, a gaming show
   broadcasts the gaming playing to all audience, and it also requires
   playing game interaction between the anchor and the audience.  A
   delay lower than 100 ms is desired.  If the delay is too large, there
   will be undesirable degradation on user experiences especially in a
   large-scale show.  To lower the latency and provide size-adjustable
   show content, the application also requires the real-time lower layer
   information.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Cloud VR" anchor="sect-2.3"><t>
   Cloud VR data volume is large which is related to different parameter
   settings like DoF (Degree of Freedom), resolution and adopted
   rendering and compression algorithm.  The rendering can be performed
   at the cloud/network side or a mix of the cloud and the user device
   side.  Because the latency in cloud VR is even as low as 20 ms, the
   application may need to interact with network to get the information
   about the segmentation or transport block information, and these
   lower layers information may be dependent on different layer 2 and
   layer 3 wireless protocol designs.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Performance Requirements of these Use Cases" anchor="sect-2.4"><t>
   There are different bandwidth, latency and lagging requirements for
   the above services which are characterized as parameter range.  The
   reason of using a range is because such requirements are related to a
   group of parameter settings including resolution, frame rate (FPS, frame per second) and the
   compression mechanism. We consider 1080p~4K as the resolution range,
   60-120 FPS (Frames per second) as the frame rate and H.265 as an
   example compression algorithm.  The end-to-end latency requirement is
   not only related to FPS but also the property of the service, i.e.,
   for weak interactive and strong interactive services.</t>

	<t>
   With the typical parameters setting, cloud gaming generally needs a
   bandwidth of 20~60 Mbps; we also consider that significant lagging
   happens when the latency is larger than 200 ms, depending on the
   types of games (e.g. 40 ms for First Person Shoot games, 80 ms for
   Action games, and 200 ms for Puzzle games).  In order to avoid bad
   user experiences, lagging is better when it is lower, and can be as low as zero (in
   an optimal QoE).  For low latency live show, 20~50 Mbps bandwidth may
   be needed and the end-to-end latency requirement is less than 100
   ms.  Cloud VR service generally requires 100~500 Mbps bandwidth and
   20~50 ms end-to-end latency.  It is noted that these values are
   dependent on the parameter settings and they are provided to
   illustrate the order of magnitude of these parameters for the aforementioned 
   use cases. These value range may be updated according to
   specific scenarios and requirements.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Current (Indirect) Technologies on NAA" anchor="sect-3"><t>
   The applications have tried to increase QoE with the help of network
   information captured from the application layer to guess the network
   dynamics, such as bitrate, buffer status, and packet loss rate.</t>

	<t>
   For example, adaptive bitrate (ABR) and buffer control methods to
   reduce delay, and application layer forward error scheme (AL-FEC) to
   avoid packet losing are proposed.  This document focuses on two novel
   approaches, which have achieved good performance in practice.  One is
   video encoding based on ROI, the other is reinforcement learning
   based adaptive bitrate.</t>

	<section title="Video Compression Based on ROI (Region of Interest)" anchor="sect-3.1"><t>
   A foveated mechanism <xref target="Saccadic"/> in the Human Visual System indicates
   that only small fovea region captures most visual attention at high
   resolution, while other peripheral regions receive little attention
   at low resolution.  And we call those regions which attract users
   most, the regions of interest (ROI)<xref target="Fahad"/>.</t>

	<t>
   To predict human attention or ROI, saliency detection has been widely
   studied in recent years, with applications in object
   recognition, object segmentation, action recognition, image caption,
   image/video compression, etc.</t>

	<t>
   Since there exists the region of interest in a video, the cloud
   server can give the ROI region higher rate while making other regions
   a lower rate.  As a result, the whole rate of the video is reduced
   while the watching experience will not be harmed.</t>

	<t>
   This method means to detect the ROI and re-allocate the coding scheme
   for interested and non-interested regions in order to save the
   bandwidth without sacrificing user's QoE.  In recent years, the ever-
   increasing video size has become a big problem to applications.  The
   data rate of a cloud gaming video in 1080P can reach 25 Mbps, which
   brings huge burden to the network, even for 5G network.  Those ROI-
   based video compression methods are mainly applied to high
   concurrency networks to relive the burden of networks and then keep
   QoE in an acceptable range.</t>

	<t>
   However, current methods utilize application information like
   application rate and application buffer size as the indicators to
   roughly adjust the algorithm in interactive video services.  That
   information is hard to reflect the real-time network status
   precisely.  Therefore, it is hard to balance the QoE and bandwidth
   saving in real-time scenario.  More direct information is helpful for
   those ROI methods to improve the performance.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="AI-based Adaptive Bitrate" anchor="sect-3.2"><t>
   This method intends to reduce lagging and ensure acceptable
   picture quality.</t>

	<t>
   Applications such as video live streaming and cloud gaming employ
   adaptive bitrate (ABR) algorithms to optimize user QoE <xref target="MPC"/><xref target="CS2P"/>.</t>

	<t>
   Despite the abundance of recently proposed schemes, state-of-the-art
   AI based ABR algorithms suffer from a key limitation.  They use fixed
   control rules based on simplified or inaccurate models of the
   deployment environment.  As a result, existing schemes inevitably
   fail to achieve optimal performance across a broad set of network
   conditions and QoE objectives.</t>

	<t>
   A reinforcement learning based ABR algorithm named Pensieve was
   proposed <xref target="Hongzi"/> recently.  Unlike traditional ABR algorithms that
   use fixed heuristics or inaccurate system models, Pensieve's ABR
   algorithms are generated using observations of the resulting
   performance of past decisions across a large number of video
   streaming experiments.  This allows Pensieve to optimize its policy
   for different network characteristics and QoE metrics directly from
   experience.  Over a broad set of network conditions and QoE metrics,
   it has been proven that Pensieve outperformed existing ABR algorithms
   by 12%~25%.</t>

	<t>
   For this method and those methods built upon this, it has been proven
   that all information, including rate, download time, buffer size or
   network level information which can reflect the performance, are
   useful to reinforcement learning.  Since those data can reflect
   the network dynamics, they have been used to help the applications to
   know how to change the rate and improve users' QoE.</t>

	<t>
   However, all these data are obtained from the client side or the
   server side.  In reality, it is not easy to obtain such data in an
   effective and efficient way.  The lacking of standardized approach to
   acquire these data makes it difficult to make this usable for different
   applications for large scale deployment. Meanwhile, since these data 
   reflect the real-time network status, they may change rapidly and randomly, 
   and hence can be hard to use a theoretical model to characterize.</t>

	<t>
   To summarize, current practices can make some improvements by
   indirectly measuring network status and react in the application.</t>

	<t>
   However, the network status data are not rich, direct, real-time; they also
   lack predictability, especially when in the mobile and wireless
   network scenarios, which results in long reaction delay or high QoE
   fluctuations.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Preliminary QoE Improvement Based on MoWIE" anchor="sect-4"><section title="MoWIE Architecture and Network Information Exposure" anchor="sect-4.1"><t>
   The fundamental idea of MoWIE is to achieve on demand and periodic
   network information from network to applications, helping network service
   providers to realize a better policy control and to improve users' experience.</t>

	<t>
   A possible MoWIE architecture includes three core components: the
   Client Application, the Mobile Network and the Application Server.</t>

	<t>
   The raw data are collected firstly from the radio network and core
   network; further processing on these collected data and
   the exposure of Network information are provided to the application Server.</t>
   
   <t>
   An application server can send network information request about UE/Cell 
   level information and obtain the NIS response on network
   information from the mobile network.  After user data pre-processing,
   the application server will make best use of the network information
   to perform analytics and directly enhance the application functions
   e.g. bit rate, latency, and jitter.</t>

	<t>
   Typically, the network information provided by MoWIE includes two types of information
   as below:</t>

	<t>
   Cell level Information:</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The number of Downlink PRBs (Physical Resource Blocks) occupied
      during sampling period;</t>

   <t>the cell load;</t>

   <t>the downklink (DL) MAC data rate per cell;</t>

   <t>the per-UE channel status (e.g. RSRP (Reference Signal Received Power) and CQI (Channel Quality Indicator));</t>

   <t>the per-UE DL data rate;</t>

   <t>the per-UE PDCP (Packet Data Convergence Protocol) buffer status;</t>

   </list></t>

	<t>
   UE level information (without privacy information):</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>The Downklink Signal to Inference plus Noise Ratio (SINR);</t>

	<t>MCS: The index of Modulation and Coding Scheme (MCS);</t>

	<t>The number of packets occupied in PDCP buffer;</t>
   
   <t>The number of downlink PDCP Service Data Unit (SDU) packets;</t>

	<t>The number of lost PDCP SDU packets;</t>

	<t>The per UE downlink MAC data rate;</t>

	</list></t>

   <t>
   The network information listed here can also be found in 3GPP (PRB <xref target="TS38.211"/>, cell load <xref target="TS38.300"/> 
   PDCP for 5G <xref target="TS38.323"/>  RSRP, RSRQ, RSSI <xref target="TS38.331"/>, MCS, CQI <xref target="TS38.214"/>, 
   The number of packets occupied in PDCP buffer, the number of Downlink PDCP SDU packets, the number of PDCP SDU packets lost, 
   the per-UE PDCP buffer status <xref target="TS38.323"/>), to demonstrate the potential benefits of MoWIE for network-application 
   integration over cellular network. Figure 3-1 and Figure 3-2 list the data types correponding 
   to the cell-level information and UE-level information, respectively.</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
            |Cell-level Information|     Data type/Range      |
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
            |         PRB          |          Uint16          |
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
            |         CQI          |          Uint8           |
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
            |        RSRP          |          Uint8           |
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
            |        RSRQ          |          Uint8           |
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
            |     Cell load        |          [0,1]           |
            +----------------------+--------------------------+
                        Figure 4-1: Cell level data type
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
            |         UE-level Information       |Data type/Range|
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
            |            Downlink SINR           |     Uint16    |
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
            |                MCS                 |     Uint8     |
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
            |      Downlink PDCP SDU packets     |     Uint8     |
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
            |    PDCP SDU packets lost           |     Uint8     |
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
            |    Packets occupied in PDCP buffer |     [0,1]     |
            +------------------------------------+---------------+
                        Figure 4-2: UE level data type
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	</section>

	<section title="RAN assisted TCP optimization based on MoWIE" anchor="sect-4.2"><t>
   The RAN information is used to assist TCP sending window adjustment
   rather than traditional transport layer measurement and
   acknowledgement.  The RAN proactively predicts available radio
   bandwidth and the buffer status per UE in a time granularity of RTT
   level (e.g. 100 ms) and then piggybacks such information in TCP ACK.</t>

	<t>
   We have conducted trial in real mobile network.  It is observed that
   for the UE with good SINR, the throughput is significantly improved
   by nearly 100%, and the UE with medium SINR can achieve approximately
   50% gain.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="NAA QoE Test based on MoWIE" anchor="sect-4.3"><t>
   Different from traditional video streaming, cloud gaming has no
   buffer to accommodate and re-arrange the received data.  It must
   display the stream once the stream is received.  Any late stream is
   of no use for the player.  Cloud gaming performs not well in the
   existing public 4G network according to our actual measurements.  The
   end to end delay is often greater than 100 ms for a gaming client in
   Shenzhen to a gaming server in Shanghai, coupled with the codec
   delay.  Here the delay is defined as the total delay from the user's
   operation instruction to show the response picture on user's screen.</t>

	<t>
   Once the network fluctuates, users will experience a longer delay.</t>

	<t>
   The poor user experience is not only because of the relative low
   network throughput, but also because that the server cannot adapt the
   application logical policies (e.g., codec scheme and data bitrate).</t>

	<t>
   The popularity of 4K and even higher resolution and increasing FPS
   for cloud gaming and AR/VR services require both high bandwidth and
   low latency in wireless and cellular networks.  The increasing
   resolution would incur a higher encoding and decoding delay.
   However, users' tolerance to delay will not increase with the
   resolution, which means the application needs to adapt to the network
   dynamics in a more efficient way.  The higher resolution, the larger
   range of the rate adaptation can be used.</t>

	<t>
   In this section, we make experiments based on the methods described
   in section 3 to improve the QoE of cloud gaming.  The performance
   between network-aware and native non-network-aware mechanisms are
   compared.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="ROI Detection with Network Information" anchor="sect-4.4"><t>
   The first experiment is based on the ROI detection.  We will
   investigate the impact of network perception.</t>

	<t>
   Saliency detection method has successfully reduced the size of videos
   and improve the QoE of users in video downloading <xref target="Saliency"/>.</t>

	<t>
   However, it is not effective when applied to real-time interactive
   streaming such as cloud gaming.</t>

	<t>
   As we know, more accurate saliency region detection algorithm needs
   more time to obtain the result.  However, when the users are
   suffering a bad performance network in cloud gaming, this precise
   detection may incur more delay to the system.  As a result, it will
   harm the final QoE.</t>

	<t>
   If the application can learn the network well in a real-time manner,
   it can choose the algorithm based on how much delay the system can
   tolerate.  If the network condition is good enough, it can adopt an
   algorithm which has deeper learning network and the added delay will
   not be perceived by the end users.  Thus, it can save huge bandwidth
   without harming the QoE.  On the other side, in a network with bad
   condition, the server can use the fastest method to avoid extra
   delay.</t>

	<t>
   We make the experiments to show how the network information will
   influence the total QoE and bandwidth saving in ROI detection.</t>

	<t>
   The following 4 methods are compared:</t>

	<t>
   1) The original video, without using ROI method.  This acts as a
   baseline.</t>

	<t>
   2) Quick saliency detection and encoding method, which is not
   accuracy in some cases.  It only brings 10ms delay.</t>

	<t>
   3) A relative accuracy saliency detection method.  In general, if an
   algorithm is more precise, it will take more time to get the results.</t>

	<t>
   And the complexity of the picture will also influence the detection
   time and accuracy.  Based on our test video, we adopt the method
   which brings delay about 40~70ms.</t>

	<t>
   4) The application server in the cloud has the current bandwidth
   information which derived from the wireless LAN NIC.  Here it is a
   simulation that all the collected bandwidth traces are already known
   by the server.  Thus, it can use the bandwidth traces to compute
   transmission delay.  Then the server can change the saliency
   detection algorithm based on this information and then encode the
   video.</t>

	<t>
   Although the result of future bandwidth prediction is not always
   accurate in real environment, the assumption here will not influence
   the final results much.  Since in cloud gaming the server encodes the
   stream based on ROI information frame by frame instead of in a grain
   of chunks, the future bandwidth prediction window size doesn't have
   to be long.  Therefore, even the server can only get the bandwidth or
   delay prediction for a short time window, the server can still use
   this method with network information.</t>

	<t>
   Test environment:</t>

	<t>
   A 720P game video segment with a rate of 6.8Mbps.  This is not a very
   high bandwidth requirement example in cloud gaming.  We just show how
   it will benefit from MoWIE.  High bandwidth requirement case will
   benefit more if the bandwidth fluctuates much.</t>

	<t>
   The three different networks are all wireless networks and the
   available bandwidth is varied frequently, where Network 1: The
   overall network condition is not very good, the average network
   bandwidth is 7.1Mbps, but it continues to fluctuate, and the minimum
   is only 3.9Mbps.</t>

	<t>
   Network 2: The overall network condition is good, with an average
   network bandwidth of 12Mbps and a minimum of 6.4Mbps.</t>

	<t>
   Network 3: The network fluctuates dramatically, with an average
   network bandwidth of 8.4Mbps and a minimum network bandwidth of
   3.7Mbps</t>

	<t>
   Test content:</t>

	<t>
   The four methods are conducted on the original video under each three
   networks.  After re-encoding based on the saliency detection, we
   calculate the new QoE and the saved bandwidth.  The results are shown
   in the Figure 4-1:</t>

	<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="-1"><t hangText="The QoE value is the MOS as standardized in the ITU.">
	<vspace blankLines="0"/>
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    +---+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
    |   |    Network 1    |    Network 2    |    Network 3    |
    +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
    |   |QoE|  BW Saving  |QoE|  BW Saving  |QoE|  BW Saving  |
    +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
    | 1 |3.8|      0      |4.8|      0      |4.3|     0       |
    +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
    | 2 |3.8|     5%      |4.8|     9%      |4.3|    7%       |
    +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
    | 3 |2.2|    2.1%     |4.6|     38%     |3.1|    34%      |
    +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
    | 4 |3.6|     9%      |4.7|     33%     |4.3|    25%      |
    +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
               Figure 4-3: QoE and Bandwidth Saving

Conclusion:
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   It can be seen that the methods such as method 2 and method 3 that do
   not rely on the network information directly, have certain
   limitations.</t>

	<t>
   Though the method 2 is simple and time-consuming, it can only detect
   a small part of region of interest accurately.  Thus, even if the
   network condition is very good, it can only save a small amount of
   bandwidth, and sometimes there are some incorrect ROI detection.  The
   QoE will be reduced without hitting the ROI region.</t>

	<t>
   For Method 3, the algorithm is complicated, and it can correctly
   detect the user's area of interest, so that it can re-allocate
   encoding scheme and save a lot of bandwidth.  However, its algorithm
   will introduce higher delay.  When the user network condition is
   poor, the extra delay will cause even worst user's QoE.  Although the
   bandwidth is saved, it affects the user experience seriously.</t>

	<t>
   Method 4 is based on the application's awareness of the network.  If
   the application can know certain network information, it can balance
   the complexity of the algorithm (introducing delay) and the accuracy
   of the algorithm (saving bandwidth) according to the actual network
   conditions.  As can be seen from the experiment, method 4 can ensure
   the user's QoE and save the bandwidth greatly at the same time.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Adaptive Bitrate with Network Capability Exposure" anchor="sect-4.5"><t>
   This experiment is AI-based rate adaption by utilizing the network
   information provided by the cellular base station (gNB) in cellular
   network.</t>

	<t>
   Tencent has launched real network testing of NAA-enabled cloud gaming
   in China Mobile LTE network, with the enhancement in gNB supporting
   base station information exposure.</t>

	<t>
   To enable the NAA mechanism, some cellular network information from
   gNBs are collected in an adaptive interval based on the change rate
   of network status.  There information is categorized in two levels,
   i.e., cell level and UE level.  Cell level information are common for
   all the UEs under a serving LTE cell and UE level information is
   specific for different UEs. 3GPP LTE specifications have specified
   how the PDCP, RLC (Radio Link
   Control), MAC (Medium Access Control) and PHY (Physical) protocols
   operate and this information are very essential statistics from these
   protocol layers.</t>

	<t>
   It is noted that in NAA mechanism, as the network information is from
   gNB, and the gNB has the real-time information of radio link quality
   statistics and layer 1 and layer 2 operation information, NAA
   mechanism can expose rich information to upper layer, e.g., it is
   capable to differentiate packet loss and congestion <xref target="MengZ"/>, which is very
   helpful to the applications in practice.</t>

	<t>
   In order to compare the cases with and without NAA, the cloud gaming
   test environment is setup with 1080p resolution and around 20Mbps
   bitrate.</t>

	<t>
   Test scenarios 1~5 are as follows.</t>

	<t>
   Test scenarios 1: Weak network.  This scenario is the case where
   radio link quality is low, e.g., in cell edge area and the bandwidth
   is not able to serve cloud gaming.</t>

	<t>
   Test scenario 2: User competition scenario.  This scenario is defined
   as the case when user amount is large thus the cellular network
   bandwidth cannot serve all the cloud gaming users.</t>

	<t>
   Test scenario 3-5: Other scenarios with random user movement trace
   and user distribution.</t>

	<t>
   Test method: To simplify to comparison, we just use the MCS (MCS
   index) information derived from the gNB <xref target="TS38.214"/>.  The information
   is provided directly to the application, and the application then
   adjusts the bit rate according to this information.  Here, MCS index
   shows the modulation (e.g.  QPSK, 16QAM,...) and the coding rate used
   during physical layer transmission, which is relevant to the real
   data rate per UE.  The benchmark method is adopting a constant bit
   rate without any information to help it predicting the network
   condition.  We compare these scenarios and observe the reduction of
   delay when those gNB data are utilized.</t>

	<t>
   For different scenarios, the lagging rate is defined as the
   performance indicator.  In our experiments, we assume lagging happens
   when transmission delay is greater than 200ms and lagging rate is
   defined as the ratio between the number of frames greater than 200ms
   and the total number of frames.</t>

	<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
            +-------------+--------------------------+
            |Test Scenario| Reduction of Lagging Rate|
            +-------------+--------------------------+
            |     1       |           46%            |
            +-------------+--------------------------+
            |     2       |           21%            |
            +-------------+--------------------------+
            |     3       |           37%            |
            +-------------+--------------------------+
            |     4       |           56%            |
            +-------------+--------------------------+
            |     5       |           32%            |
            +-------------+--------------------------+
              Figure 4-4: Reduction of Lagging Rate
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
   It can be clearly seen that with the MCS information, the application
   can adjust the bit rate to decrease the lagging rate and then
   significantly improve the user QoE.  In weak network scenario, 46%
   lagging can be avoided by NAA.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Analysis of the Experiments" anchor="sect-4.6"><t>
   The above-mentioned technologies demonstrate the performance gain of
   NAA with MoWIE.</t>

	<t>
   Although application information can also help to predict the network
   and have already been used in adaptive bit rate methods, the
   application information is not as sensitive as gNB information at the
   very beginning in a lot of cases.  For example, when more users enter
   the cell, the PRB information will first reflect that each user may
   get less bandwidth.  However, the application information needs to
   react after there is a trend that the bitrate is decreasing.  That is
   to say, the lower layer network information is more directly.</t>

	<t>
   Without MoWIE, the application cannot get the lower layer network
   information directly and then try to detect "blindly" to adapt to the
   dynamics of the lower layer network, which cannot meet the
   requirements of cloud interactive applications like cloud gaming, low
   delay live show and Cloud VR.</t>

	<t>
   It is noted that the more real-time network resource status the
   application can learn, the better it can predict how much network
   resource it can use within a prediction time window.  However, there
   is tradeoff between network information collection frequency and its
   load and feasibility to the network devices.  In principle, the total
   network resource consumed for such network status reporting is also
   designed in light-weight manner, e.g., by properly controlling the
   interval of report and also the number of bits needed to convey the
   reported information elements.  In our experiments, the network
   status information can be obtained in an adaptive interval based on
   the change rate of network status, in order to provide good
   prediction with less load introduced in the network.  In fact, not
   all scenarios need a very frequent information collection.  If some
   information only changes in a very small range and won't influence
   the final decision, it is unnecessary to report such information all
   the time.  However, if its value varies over the preset threshold, it
   will inform the application immediately.</t>

	<t>
   The distribution and impact of the exposed data to the performance
   gain for different algorithm needs to be further studied.  This draft
   is to give a guidance to figure out what kind of data needs to be
   exposed during initial deployment of these mechanisms.</t>

	<t>
   In our current cloud gaming, the application information can help to
   reduce about 50% the lagging rate.  The left 50% improvement room can
   be achieved by network information exposure with MoWIE.  Actually,
   the effect of the two-layer information can be accumulated.  However,
   due to current deployment limitation, we cannot collect the
   application information with the gNB information at the same time.
   Thus, in this version of the draft we compare the performance with
   and without MoWIE.  We don't compare between application information
   assisted mode and network information assisted mode in this draft.
   This is our on- going work.  Since both application and gNB
   information can reflect the network variation, we will compare the
   performance among application information assisted mode, network
   information assisted mode and the mode of utilizing both layer
   information.</t>

	</section>

	</section>

	<section title="Standardization Considerations of MoWIE as an Extension to ALTO" anchor="sect-5"><t>
    In 3GPP, network information exposure based on control plane mechanism is introduced in 4G and 5G systems. 
    In 3GPP Release 17, there is a work item named 5G_AIS (Advanced Interactive Services) which focuses on 
    QoS enhancements for interactive services including cloud gaming, XR, remote driving and real-time digital 
    twin. There is also continuous work in Release 18 XRM (XR and media services). Among these two work items, 
    one important way to support QoS enhancements is to expose the network status information to the application layer 
    and the application layer can take measures to adapt according to the network status information. The network information 
    can include the radio network statistics as has been elaborated in Section 4.1 and also the parameters specified
    in <xref target="ALTO_METRICS"/>. In Section 4.1, the parameters which MoWIE proposes to expose can provide real-time status 
    and rich information about the wireless link which can be utilized by AI-ML (Machine Learning) algorithms
    to predict the available network resources in the subsequent transmission opportunities, which can help the 
    application layer to adjust its traffic pattern or codec profile to optimize the user’s experience. 
    By mapping these parameters with the ALTO metrics which has been proposed or define potential new ALTO metrics, 
    it is possible to extent current ALTO protocols to provide better support for real-time immersive services. 
    In ETSI MEC, RNIS <xref target="ETSI_MEC"/> has proposed to expose physical layer, Layer 2 and higher layer 
    parameters including 4G and 5G. There are some common parameters like RSRP, RSRQ and RSSI which MoWIE also proposes; 
    however, RNIS is based on the MEC architecture, and MoWIE is not restricted to MEC case.</t>

    <t>
   It should be noticed that the previous mechanisms may also work on
   IEEE 802.11 standards (e.g., EHT), helping SP having a better
   understanding for the network environment between AP and STAs.  Based
   on the fact that 802.11 devices are working on unlicensed spectrums,
   and easily influenced by adjacent unlicensed devices, duty cycle and
   related CQI information (e.g., MCS, and bandwidth) are considered very important network information here.Standardization
   Considerations of MoWIE as an Extension to ALTO MoWIE can be a
   realistic, important extension to ALTO to serve the aforementioned
   use cases, in the setting of the newer generation (5G) of cellular
   network, which is a completely open IP based network where routers/
   UPF with IP connectivity will be deployed much closer to the users.
   One may consider not only the aforementioned cloud- based multimedia
   applications, but also other latency sensitive applications such as
   connected vehicles and automotive driving.</t>

	<t>
   Extending ALTO with MoWIE, therefore, may allow ALTO to expose lower
   layer network information to ensure higher application QoE for a wide
   spectrum of applications.</t>

	<t>
   One possible approach to standardizing the distribution of the
   network information used in the evaluations is to send such
   information as piggyback information in the datapath.  One issue with
   datapath method is that MoWIE intends to convey more complex and rich
   information than current methods.  To piggyback such complex and rich
   information in the datapath will consume significant datapath
   resource.  But the datapath-based method can provide frequent changed
   network information and it is technically simpler to synchronize the network
   information and user data at the same time scale. Normally, there is
   less user data in the uplink direction and the free "space"
   within the MTU can be used to piggyback the network informaton to
   the application, without the additional overhead of creating a second
   communication channel between the application and network.  However,
   the datapath design may bring out more limited privacy management,
   which is very important in MoWIE.  The application cannot trust the
   network information if there is no message authentication mechanism
   for the piggyback network information.  How the network inserts the
   network information in the data packet is also challengeable since a
   lot of transport layer protocol are encrypted and integration
   protected.  Another method is to create an associated path aligned
   with datapath.  Like the ICMP for IP and RTCP for RTP, this second
   path can be used to provide additional information associated with
   the datapath.  But creating such second path is a big change to
   current widely used transport protocols and a lot of applications
   also need to change, this second path is also challengeable.</t>
        
        
    <t>In this draft, we mainly discuss ALTO extension-based design in tackling with this problem.	
    Specifically, the MoWIE extension will reuse existing ALTO mechanisms including 
    information resource directory, extensible performance metrics and calendaring, and unified properties.
    Below is an overview of key considerations; security
   considerations are in the following section.</t>

	<t><list style="symbols"><t>Network information selection and binding consideration: Instead
      of hardcoding only specific network information, a modular design
      of MoWIE is an ability for an ALTO client to select only the
      relevant information (e.g., cell DLOccupyPRBNum metric and UE MCS)
      and then request correspondingly.  Existing ALTO information
      resource directory is a starting point, but the design needs to be
      generic," to provide abstraction for ease of use and extensibility.  The security mechanisms of the existing ALTO protocol should also be extended to enforce proper authorization.</t>

	<t>Compact network information encoding consideration: One benefit of
      ALTO is its high-level JSON based encoding.  When the update
      frequency increases, the existing base protocol and existing
      extensions (in particular the SSE extension), however, may have
      high bandwidth and processing overhead.  Hence, encoding and
      processing overhead of MoWIE should be considered.</t>

	<t>Stability and reliability consideration: A key benefit of the
      MoWIE extension is the ability to allow more flexible, better
      coordinated control.  Any control mechanism, however, should
      integrate fundamental overhead, stability and reliability
      mechanisms.</t>

    <t>Cost metrics considerations. In <xref target="ALTO_METRICS"/>, some cost metrics are 
        being standardized including throughput/bit rate, latency, priority, error rate, 
        jitter. These parameters can be linked with cost metrics in 5G network entities like NEF <xref target="TS23.501"/> 
        or AF <xref target="TS23.501"/>. NEF or AF, which act as ALTO Clients, utilizing the network information exposure 
        capability provided by 3GPP standards, can request to expose some of the proposed parameters with 
        consideration of the ALTO performance metrics.</t>

	</list>
	</t>
   
   <t>By extending the exposure scope of network information beyond the cellular access,
    ALTO can help improve the QoE of several applications running on endpoints located in cellular networks.
     <xref target="ALTO_USE_CASES"/> is work in progress that investigates use cases where the performances of these applications 
     can be further improved with abstracted network information and suitable transportation means provided by ALTO.
      Additionally, upon reviewing the existing ALTO capabilities, it lists the ALTO features that need to be extended 
      or defined to support the presented use cases. A next step is to thoroughly apply this analysis to the metrics 
      envisaged by MoWIE, given the constraints of both the applications and ALTO.
 </t>

	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sect-6"><t>
   This document has no actions for IANA.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sect-7"><t>
   The collection, distribution of MoWIE information should consider the
   security requirements on information privacy and information
   integration protection and authentication in both sides.  Since the
   network status is not directly related to any special user, there is
   currently no any privacy issue.  But the information transmitted to
   the application can pass through a lot of middle box and can be
   changed by the man in the middle.  To protect the network
   information, an end to end encryption and integration is needed.
   Also, the network needs to authenticate the information exposure
   provided to right applications.  These security requirements can be
   implemented by the TLS and other security mechanisms.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="sect-8"><t>
   The authors would like to thank Huang Wei for his contribution to the
   previous drafts.</t>

	</section>

	</middle>

	<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
	&RFC2474;
	&RFC3168;
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
	<reference anchor="CS2P" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2934872.2934898"><front>
	<title>CS2P: Improving Video Bitrate Selection and Adaptation with Data-Driven Throughput Prediction</title>
	<author>
	<organization>Sun, Yi., Yin, Xiaoqi., Jiang, Junchen., Sekar, Vyas., Lin, Fuyuan., Wang, Nanshu., Liu, Tao., and Bruno. Sinopoli</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2016"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2934872.2934898"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="Fahad" target="https://doi.org/10.1109/SITIS.2011.84"><front>
	<title>A Novel Visual Saliency Model for Surveillance Video Compression</title>
	<author>
	<organization>Fazal Elahi Guraya, Fahad., Alaya Cheikh, Faouzi., and Victor. Medina</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2011"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/SITIS.2011.84"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="Hongzi" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3098822.3098843"><front>
	<title>Neural Adaptive Video Streaming with Pensieve</title>
	<author>
	<organization>Mao, Hongzi., Netravali, Ravi., and Mohammad. Alizadeh</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2017"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3098822.3098843"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="MPC" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2785956.2787486"><front>
	<title>A Control-Theoretic Approach for Dynamic Adaptive Video Streaming over HTTP</title>
	<author>
	<organization>Yin, Xiaoqi., Jindal, Abhishek., Sekar, Vyas., and Bruno. Sigopoli</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2015"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2785956.2787486"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="MPEGDASH" target="https://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-dash"><front>
	<title>ISO/IEC 23009, Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP</title>
	<author>
	<organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2020"/>
	</front>

	</reference>
	<reference anchor="Saccadic" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/h0037368"><front>
	<title>Saccadic suppression: A review and an analysis</title>
	<author initials="E." surname="Matin" fullname="E. Matin">
	</author>

	<date year="1974"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1037/h0037368"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="Saliency" target="https://doi.org/10.1109/TIP.2009.2030969"><front>
	<title>A Novel Multiresolution Spatiotemporal Saliency Detection Model and Its Applications in Image and Video Compression</title>
	<author initials="C." surname="Guo" fullname="C. Guo">
	</author>

	<author initials="L." surname="Zhang" fullname="L. Zhang">
	</author>

	<date year="2017"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/TIP.2009.2030969"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="TS23.501" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3144"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2021"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;System" value="architecture for the 5G System (5GS)&quot;"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="ALTO_METRICS" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-alto-performance-metrics-09"><front>
	<title>Internet-Draft, draft-ietf-alto-performance-metrics-09</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2020"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="ALTO Performance Cost Metrics&quot;"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="TS26.114" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=1404"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2021"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;IP" value="Multimedia Subsystem (IMS); Multimedia telephony; Media handling and interaction&quot;"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="TS26.247" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=1444"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2020"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;Progressive" value="Download and Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP(3GP-DASH)&quot;"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="TS38.211" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3213"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2017"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Physical channels and modulation&quot;"/>
	</reference>  

	<reference anchor="TS38.214" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3216"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2021"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Physical layer procedures for data&quot;"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="TS38.300" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3191"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2017"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="NR and NG-RAN Overall description; Stage-2&quot;"/>
	</reference>

    <reference anchor="TS38.323" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3196"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2017"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Packet Data Convergence Protocol (PDCP) specification&quot;"/>
	</reference> 

    <reference anchor="TS38.331" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3197"><front>
	<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2017"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Protocol specification&quot;"/>
	</reference>

   <reference anchor="ETSI_MEC" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_gs/MEC/"><front>
	<title>ETSI GS MEC 012</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2019"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;Multi-access Edge Computing (MEC);" value="Radio Network Information API&quot;"/>
	</reference>

   <reference anchor="ALTO_USE_CASES" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-li-alto-cellular-use-cases"><front>
	<title>Internet-Draft, draft-li-alto-cellular-use-cases-00</title>
	<author>
	</author>

	<date year="2021"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="ALTO Uses Cases for Cellular Networks&quot;"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="PBECC" target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.1145/3387514.3405880"><front>
	<title>PBE-CC: Congestion control via endpoint-centric, physical-layer bandwidth measurements</title>
	<author>
	<organization>Xie, Yaxiong, Fan Yi, and Kyle Jamieson</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2020"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3387514.3405880"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="MengZ" target="https://zilimeng.com/papers/zhuge-sigcomm22.pdf"><front>
	<title>Achieving Consistent Low Latency for Wireless Real-Time Communications with the Shortest Control Loop</title>
	<author>
	<organization>Meng, Z., Guo, Y., Sun, C., Wang, B., Sherry, J., Liu, H. H., Xu, M. (2022)</organization>
	</author>

	<date year="2022"/>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3544216.3544225"/>
	</reference>

	</references>
    
	</back>

	</rfc>
	
